{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man dispatched dragoons to kidnap the Duc d’Enghien [“duke” den-gh’yen]. This man, who was prohibited from joining the army due to a foot injury in his youth, was removed from one of his posts after embracing the notorious Civil Constitution of the Clergy. This one-time Bishop of Autun demanded bribes of American diplomats in 1797. For ten points, name this French diplomat who represented France during the Congress of Vienna and instigated the XYZ Affair.",
      "answer": "Charles-Maurice de Talleyrand Perigord"
    },
    {
      "question": "This president signed the Matthew Shepard Hate Crimes Prevention Act, which expanded the 1969 federal hate-crimes law and required the FBI to track statistics on hate crimes on the basis of gender. Other major statutes passed under this president include the Ledbetter Fair Pay Act and a repeal of the Don’t Ask, Don’t Tell policy. This president issued the DACA and DAPA executive orders on immigration and enacted the Dodd-Frank Act. For ten points, name this president, after whom the Affordable Care Act was nicknamed.",
      "answer": "Barack Obama"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Georgios Averof managed to perform this action during the Battle of Elli. This devastating feat was most recently carried out by Jesse Oldendorf against the enemy line during the Battle of Surigao Strait. Zinovy Rozhestvensky was decisively defeated by a performance of this action that relied on wireless telegraphy to coordinate Admiral Togo’s orders. During the Battle of Tsushima Strait, the Japanese fleet was twice able to pull off, for ten points, what now-obsolete naval maneuver, performed by traveling perpendicular to a line of enemy ships?",
      "answer": "crossing the T or capping the T"
    },
    {
      "question": "This woman served as the first president of the New England Woman Suffrage Association, and her husband Samuel was a member of the Secret Six. A pacifist Mother’s Day Proclamation was issued by this woman, who wrote a work that describes a figure who “loosed the fateful lightning of His terrible swift sword;” that work adopted the melody used in “John Brown’s Body” and repeats the line “glory, glory, hallelujah!” For ten points, name this lyricist of the “Battle Hymn of the Republic.”",
      "answer": "Julia Ward Howe"
    },
    {
      "question": "Prussia’s King Frederick William IV commissioned this man to write music for a play featuring the song “Ye spotted snakes.” Queen Victoria once claimed her favorite piece by this man was a song actually composed by his sister, Fanny. A visit to the ruins of Holyrood Chapel inspired this man’s third symphony, as well as his Hebrides Overture. The Scottish Symphony was composed by, for ten points, what composer whose music for A Midsummer Night’s Dream features a famous “Wedding March?”",
      "answer": "Felix Mendelssohn-Bartholdy"
    },
    {
      "question": "This institution was heavily damaged in a Christmas Eve 1851 fire that destroyed the majority of its holdings. Charles Coffin Jewett competed with this organization while working for the Smithsonian. Ainsworth Rand Spofford wanted to make this institution a “repository of American culture” and lobbied for it to receive two copies of copyrighted items. After this institution was sacked by the British, Thomas Jefferson sold his personal collection to it. For ten points, name this institution, the de facto national library of the United States.",
      "answer": "Library of Congress"
    },
    {
      "question": "Bayesian games model this value as a probability distribution. Michael Spence identified education as a “costly signal” of this value in a job market model, which described one method of its transmission. George Akerlof’s 1970 paper “The Market for Lemons” used the example of used car dealerships to discuss the asymmetry of this value. For ten points, name this economic concept that is “perfect” if both actors have complete knowledge.",
      "answer": "information"
    },
    {
      "question": "A ruler of this country formally became its king at the Congress of Lutsk, but died before the crown could physically reach him. A leader of this country defeated Skirgaila before signing the Astrava treaty with Jogaila, allowing him to replace Skirgaila as regent of this country. Vytautas ruled this country, which joined with its southwestern neighbor in the Union of Krewo and the Union of Lublin. For ten points, name this Grand Duchy that formed a commonwealth with Poland.",
      "answer": "Grand Duchy of Lithuania"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was prominently supported by Paul Scoon, who was liberated from house arrest during it. After a lengthy air assault, Army Rangers seized Port Salines International Airport during this event. Hudson Austin fell from power and the New Jewel Movement dissolved as a result of this event, which was codenamed “Operation Urgent Fury.” The execution of Maurice Bishop triggered, for ten points, what 1983 military action ordered by Ronald Reagan against a Caribbean island nation?",
      "answer": [
        "United States’ invasion of Grenada",
        "clear equivalents for invasion, like occupation"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Kathleen Lynch cites the presence of bones of “butchered animals” as evidence that the Persians did not commit this action as a deliberate military tactic. Finnish soldiers committed this action using animal feces during their retreat in the Winter War. In the aftermath of the Kanto Earthquake, Koreans were often attacked after being accused of doing this. Synagogues were attacked during the Middle Ages as Jews were falsely blamed for spreading the plague via, for ten points, what specific type of biological warfare?",
      "answer": [
        "poisoning water",
        "more specific answers, like poisoning wells"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The European Medical Agency was placed in this city in 1995, along with the European Banking Authority in 2011. This city’s Docklands area was revitalized in the 1980s, and its Canary Wharf has since become a major financial center, alongside its more traditional City. Ken Livingstone became this metropolis’s first elected mayor in 2000 and promised reforms including “bendy” buses to replace its iconic two-story buses. For ten points, name this economic center of Britain.",
        "answer": "London"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This tourist attraction on the south bank of the Thames was built in 2000 and was the subject of a rent dispute in 2005, which mayor Livingstone helped resolve.",
        "answer": "the London Eye"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Fazal Ali commission was created by this man to reorganize states. This man used the Forward Policy to fight China over the Line of Actual Control. V. K. Menon served as this man’s secretary of defense before resigning after the 1962 Sino-Indian War. In one speech, this man declared “the light has gone out of our lives” after the assassination of his mentor; in another speech, he discussed a “Tryst with Destiny.” Indira Gandhi was the daughter of, for ten points, what first prime minister of India?",
        "answer": "Jawarhalal Nehru"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nehru’s eulogy for Mahatma Gandhi was delivered just hours after this Hindu nationalist shot Gandhi.",
        "answer": "Nathuram Godse"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A close confidant of this tsar was a liberal reformer named Mikhail Speransky. This tsar’s forces were commanded by Levin August von Bennigsen at the Battle of Eylau. This tsar rose to power after the assassination of his predecessor, Paul I. Supporters advocating for the succession of this man’s brother Constantine led a revolt in Saint Petersburg after this man’s death in 1825. The Treaties of Tilsit were signed during the reign of, for ten points, what early nineteenth century tsar who clashed with Napoleon?",
        "answer": "Alexander I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The rebels in this 1825 uprising after the death of Alexander chanted “Constantine and Constitution!”, but were suppressed by Nicholas I.",
        "answer": "Decembrist revolt or uprising, etc."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This chief justice joined a dissent by Samuel Nelson in holding that only Congress has the power to declare war in the Prize Cases. This justice argued for a narrow interpretation of contracts and for community rights in his majority opinion in a dispute between the Warren Bridge and the Charles River Bridge. This man stated that Article 3 of the Constitution did not give African-Americans citizenship in what is often seen as one of the Supreme Court’s worst verdicts. For ten points, name this Chief Justice during the Dred Scott decision.",
        "answer": "Roger Taney , but be lenient"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Before his appointment to the Supreme Court, Taney was part of this group of presidential advisers that included Amos Kendall and John Overton.",
        "answer": [
          "Andrew Jackson’s Cabinet",
          "descriptions of Jackson’s actual Cabinet and/or Jackson’s unofficial Kitchen Cabinet"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a play that mocks this war, a farmer disguises his daughters as pigs and trades them for salt, while the main character holds a basket of charcoal hostage while trying to argue for an end to this war. In another play, a man flies a dung beetle to heaven to argue for an end to this war. A cause of this war was an embargo against the colony of Megara, as related in the play The Acharnians. Aristophanes’s comedy Peace satirizes the motives of general Cleon’s actions in, for ten points, what war between Athens and Sparta?",
        "answer": "Peloponnesian War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This historian included an account of an unsuccessful diplomatic negotiation between emissaries of Athens and Melos in his History of the Peloponnesian War.",
        "answer": "Thucydides"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One man with this surname was convinced by Edwin Land to override the Air Force and develop the U2 plane. The “Pactomania” period of forming extensive alliances was overseen by a man with this surname who also developed the doctrines of massive retaliation and brinkmanship to counter Soviet strength. One man with this surname served as Eisenhower’s Secretary of State, and his brother oversaw the failed Bay of Pigs invasion as head of the CIA. For ten points, give the surname of 1950s American diplomats Allen and John Foster.",
        "answer": [
          "Dulles",
          "John Foster Dulles and/or Allen Dulles"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Allen Dulles launched Operation PBSUCCESS in this country, where a CIA-backed coup led to the removal of Jacobo Arbenz.",
        "answer": "Guatemala"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This function is applied to initial mass over final mass in an equation published in 1903 by Konstantin Tsiolkovsky for the behavior of rockets. Leibniz introduced the modern notation for this function and related it to the integral of 1 over x. This function was discovered and popularized by John Napier, and Henry Briggs compiled a table of these functions and changed them into base 10. For ten points, name this function whose “natural” example uses e as its base, the inverse of the exponential function.",
        "answer": "natural logarithm"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The base of the natural logarithm, e, is named for this blind Swiss mathematician.",
        "answer": "Leonhard Euler , but be lenient"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this conflict, the Ariovistus-led Suebi tribe was defeated. Diviciacus [DIV-ik-ee-ah-kus] warned one side of a conspiracy before these wars, though his people, the Aedui [aid-wee], later flipped allegiances. The losing side in this war did not burn Gergovia or Avaricum, despite a scorched earth strategy, and the winning side built bridges over the Rhine, then burned them as a show of force. In the crucial battle of this war, a double wall was built around Vercingetorix’s forces in Alesia. For ten points, name this set of wars that allowed Julius Caesar to subjugate modern-day France.",
        "answer": [
          "Gallic Wars",
          "descriptions of wars between the Gauls and the Romans"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Roman-Gallic tension existed long before the Gallic Wars; during the 390 BC sack of Rome, this Senone leader legendarily shouted “woe to the vanquished” while demanding more tribute.",
        "answer": "Brennus"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "James Garfield",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Vice President who succeeded Garfield.",
          "answer": "Chester Alan Arthur"
        },
        {
          "question": "Stalwart assassin who killed Garfield.",
          "answer": "Charles Guiteau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former president and Civil War general who Garfield narrowly beat at the 1880 Republican National Convention.",
          "answer": "Ulysses S. Grant"
        },
        {
          "question": "Major Union victory in Tennessee in which Garfield participated and Albert Sidney Johnston was killed.",
          "answer": "Battle of Shiloh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Home state of Garfield’s rival, fellow Republican Roscoe Conkling.",
          "answer": "New York"
        },
        {
          "question": "Monetary concept that was retroactively increased in an 1873 act that cost Republicans the House and nearly cost Garfield his seat.",
          "answer": [
            "Congressional salaries",
            "descriptive answers,"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Court case that Garfield argued, concerning five Hoosiers who were improperly tried in a military tribunal.",
          "answer": "Ex parte Milligan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Letters detailing bribes paid to James Blaine that sunk his 1876 and 1880 presidential campaigns.",
          "answer": "Mulligan Letters"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "German unification",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "“Iron Chancellor” who led Germany after its unification.",
          "answer": "Otto von Bismarck"
        },
        {
          "question": "German state whose monarch ruled Germany after unification.",
          "answer": [
            "Prussia",
            "Preussen"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "French palace whose Hall of Mirrors was the location of Germany’s unification.",
          "answer": "Versailles"
        },
        {
          "question": "German state dissolved by unification ruled by Ludwig the “Swan King” before 1871.",
          "answer": [
            "Bavaria",
            "Bayern"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-Catholic struggle of the German government after unification.",
          "answer": "Kulturkampf"
        },
        {
          "question": "Antecedent to a unified Germany established by Napoleon after conquering states along a namesake river.",
          "answer": "Confederation of the Rhine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Customs union proposed by Friedrich List as a forerunner to a unified German state.",
          "answer": "Zollverein"
        },
        {
          "question": "Philosopher who proposed a concept of Volksgeist to explain what he theorized was the German nation.",
          "answer": "Johann von Herder"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Singapore",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country from which Singapore was expelled in 1965.",
          "answer": "Malaysia"
        },
        {
          "question": "British Prime Minister who called the fall of colonial Singapore the worst disaster in British military history.",
          "answer": "Winston Churchill"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Prime Minister of an independent Singapore.",
          "answer": "Lee Kuan Yew"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that fought the Konfrontasi conflict against Singapore under the leadership of Sukarno.",
          "answer": "Indonesia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Regional organisation that Singapore helped found in 1967. Its ten member states include Laos, Brunei, and Thailand.",
          "answer": "Association of Southeast Asian Nations or ASEAN"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political party that has ruled Singapore since its independence.",
          "answer": "People’s Action Party or PAP"
        },
        {
          "question": "British statesman who conquered Java and established British Singapore.",
          "answer": "Sir Stamford Raffles"
        },
        {
          "question": "1822 urban plan for Singapore, outlined by that statesman and named for the lieutenant engineer who designed it.",
          "answer": "Jackson Plan"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Dave Paulson was questioned for his role in this event after his business card was left in a police car with a suspicious note on it. Twelve years prior to this event, a group called The Covenant, the Sword, and the Arm of the Lord planned a rocket (20 pts)",
        "attack on the same target. Missing license plates prompted Charlie Hanger to arrest the perpetrator of this event, who was inspired to commit it after the (10 pts)",
        "ATF siege of the Branch Davidian compound at Waco. Terry Nichols and Timothy McVeigh carried out, for ten points, what 1968 attack on the Alfred P. Murrah Building?"
      ],
      "answer": "Oklahoma City bombing"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A self-portrait done as one of this author’s characters includes a portrait of the painter Emile Bernard in the background and was dedicated to van Gogh, who called it “ill and tormented.” A nude sculpture for this man’s memorial shows him beneath waves off the isle of (20 pts)",
        "Guernsey. While in exile for his Republican views, this man wrote pamphlets against Napoleon III and a novel that includes a lengthy description of (10 pts)",
        "Waterloo. Paul Gauguin painted himself as one of this man’s creations, the convict Jean Valjean. For ten points, name this French author of Les Miserables."
      ],
      "answer": "Victor Marie Hugo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a show on this network, Timothy Olyphant plays Seth Bullock and characters like Calamity Jane and Wild Bill Hickok live in the title South Dakota city. Deadwood was a show on this network, which also created a series based on a Stephen (20 pts)",
        "Ambrose book that focuses on Easy Company’s experience in World War II. A David McCullough biography inspired another miniseries on this TV network starring Paul Giamatti as a (10 pts)",
        "president from colonial Massachusetts. Band of Brothers and John Adams were produced by, for ten points, what premium TV network whose far less historical shows include Game of Thrones?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "HBO",
        "Home Box Office"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Upon its discovery, the Kendall Ring was believed to have been worn by a resident of this location; recent testing suggests that ring is brass instead of gold. The Zuniga Map specifically notes the location of four residents of this location. When John White did not (20 pts)",
        "find the shape of a Maltese Cross upon his return to this location in (10 pts)",
        "1590, he was baffled. Sir Walter Raleigh ordered the founding of this colony, whose inhabitants carved the word “CROATOAN” into a post before its abandonment. For ten points, identify this British “lost colony” established on a namesake North Carolina island."
      ],
      "answer": "Roanoke Colony"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this man’s premiership, Alexei Larionov tripled production of meat in his native oblast during the Ryazan Miracle. A desire to “show the United States a Kuzma’s mother” prompted researchers to carry out a (20 pts)",
        "nuclear test on Novaya Zemlya. This man only showed interest in the cafeteria during a visit to (10 pts)",
        "IBM headquarters. The most powerful explosion on Earth, the Tsar Bomba test, was carried out at the beginning of the premiership of, for ten points, what Soviet premier who visited the United States six years after succeeding Stalin?"
      ],
      "answer": "Nikita Khrushchev"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A symbolic defeat for this religion occurred when the “bora winds” redirected one side’s arrows back at the archers during the Battle of the Frigid River. Members of this religion, who twice had their “Altar of (20 pts)",
        "Victory” desecrated, faced new restrictions after the Theodosian Decrees were issued. As the last (10 pts)",
        "emperor to follow this religion, Julian was known as the Apostate. This religion was overshadowed by a monotheistic faith after the Edict of Milan. For ten points, name this ancient religion that, before it was supplanted by Christianity, officially honored Janus, Jupiter, and Mars."
      ],
      "answer": "traditional Roman religion"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1984, a snap election in this country became known as the “schnapps election” due to the drinking habits of the ousted Prime Minister. In this country, Alain Mafart was part of a team that planted a bomb that killed photographer Fernando Pereira; (20 pts)",
        "French Defense Minister Charles Hernu resigned as a result of that action. Prime Minister David Lange instituted (10 pts)",
        "Rogernomics in this country, where Greenpeace docked the ship Rainbow Warrior before its bombing in 1985. For ten points, name this country where Robert Muldoon once served as Prime Minister in its capital Wellington."
      ],
      "answer": "New Zealand"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man replaced “The False Monk” in the Synod of Brixen, and his son signed the Concordat of Worms. Robert Guiscard forced this man’s retreat from Rome. This man beat forces under Otto of Nordheim at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Langensalza while Rudolf of Rheinfelden revolted against this man in the Great Saxon Revolt. Wearing a hairshirt, this man repented while (10 pts)",
        "traveling to Matilda of Tuscany’s castle. This man embarked on the Walk to Canossa during a conflict with Pope Gregory VII. For ten points, name this Holy Roman Emperor who suffered excommunication during the Lay Investiture Controversy."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Holy Roman Emperor Henry IV",
        "Henry VIII of Bavaria"
      ]
    }
  ]
}